<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter apologeticall of George Brisse Lord of Desgrutieres wherein are set downe the reasons that moued him to turne to the reformed. / Written to Monsieur Touraine, Aduocate in the Court of Parliament of Bretany. A worke very profitable for those to reade that desire to know the grounds of their religion. Translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Lettre apologétique de George Brisset, Sr Desgrustières. English.</title>
            <author>Brisset, Georges.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854512</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19938</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16898)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19938)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter apologeticall of George Brisse Lord of Desgrutieres wherein are set downe the reasons that moued him to turne to the reformed. / Written to Monsieur Touraine, Aduocate in the Court of Parliament of Bretany. A worke very profitable for those to reade that desire to know the grounds of their religion. Translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Lettre apologétique de George Brisset, Sr Desgrustières. English.</title>
                  <author>Brisset, Georges.</author>
                  <author>Tauraine, Monsieur.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Richard Lea, and are to be sold at his shop at the North entry of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Georges Brisset: Lettre apologétique de George Brisset, Sr Desgrustières, sur les raisons qui l'ont meu à se ranger à la religion réformée.</note>
                  <note>Another translation of the French original exists under the title: The apologie of George Brisset, Lord of Gratence (STC 3791).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19938:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19938:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER APOLOGETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL OF GEORGE BRISSE Lord of Deſgru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieres, wherein are ſet downe the reaſons that moued him to turne to the Reformed.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN TO MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur TOVRAINE, Aduocate in the Court of Parliament of BRETANY.</p>
            <p>A WORKE VERY PROFITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for thoſe to reade that deſire to know the grounds of their Religion.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, printed by G. ELD for RICHARD LEA, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the North entry of the Royall Exchange, 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19938:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19938:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Epiſtle to the</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to ſerue GOD is the part of a Chriſtian, ſo how to ſerue him aright is the part of a wiſe Chriſtian to learne. I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued if this Booke doe not teach that; and therefore cannot receiue too much applauſe. This ſuperstitious age is lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in Mariage to hereſie, who haue begot many impious Infants, I meane bookes both ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and blaſphemous written by Sectaries, but eſpecially by the Romiſh writers. The moſt groſſe errors of whom this Treatiſe vnfolds. Thanke the Author for the Worke, Mee for the tranſlation, and GOD for both. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19938:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19938:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F heretofore you haue done mee the honour to repute mee a man of deſert, and haue beene deſirous of my ſaluation, I deſire that now alſo you would haue mee in the like eſteeme. To the end therefore that my al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of religion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print in you no hard conceit of mee, I haue thought it fit to ſet downe the motiues, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which haue induced mee to this change; beſeeching you to beleeue (and my GOD knowes that I lie not) that I haue not had regard to any humane conſiderations, but on the contrarie haue not harkened to the promiſes and promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Romane Church offered vnto me; and haue loſt the friendſhip of many perſonages, whom neuertheleſſe I will not leaue to loue, and honour, and you principally, Sir, whoſe vertue,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19938:4"/>and good opinion I haue euer much eſteemed, and deſired. Theſe conſiderations infuſe a hope into mee that you will relliſh well my reaſons, which briefely, and ſummarily I will here ſet downe.</p>
            <p>Giue me leaue then to tell you, Sir, that when I was the moſt zealouſly addicted to the Romane Religion, I had notwithſtanding this perſwaſion that Religion is not ſubject to men, how great and learned ſoeuer they be, but that they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Religion. I alſo then held Religion to be the Rule of ſaluation giuen by GOD to men, to which euery man ought to be ſubjected, it being not permitted to any one to exempt himſelfe, or to change, or diminiſh it. And thereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of ſome of the Roman Church (whom I reputed the moſt learned) where this Rule was giuen by GOD, they anſwered that it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that booke commonly called the Bible, and that it was peculiar to this booke onely to be ſtiled the <hi>Word of GOD.</hi> According to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (hauing firſt inuoked GOD for increaſe of knowledge) I ſet my ſelfe to reade this booke, and hauing read intentiuely all the Goſpell, I was much aſtoniſhed to finde almoſt nothing in it that had beene taught me. I plainely perceiued that it was not there commanded to inuoke the Saints, nor to render any ſeruice to Images, nor to ſacrifice IESVS CHRIST, nor to adore the Hoaſt, nor to pray to GOD without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: I alſo clearely ſaw that there was no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19938:4"/>made of Purgatorie, nor of Lent, nor of Maſſes, nor of Merits, nor of Monkes, nor of diuerſe Orders of Religion, nor of the Primacy of the Roman Church. In a word, I found few things there, which I thought to be expreſsly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>Word of GOD;</hi> nay quite contrary, I found many paſſages contradictory to thoſe things which in former time I had learned.</p>
            <p>Being in this Labyrinth, I thought the next way to get out was, to addreſſe my ſelfe to ſome of the greateſt Schollers of that Religion, and to implore their aide. Which I did, and receiued this anſwere from them, that it was not for mee to reade the Holy Scripture, and to enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things which paſſed my capacity. Alſo they told mee that the Catholicke Roman Church had ſo ordained, to which the holy Scripture ſends vs, ſaying that it is the pillar and the prop of Verity. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. verſ. 15. Who heares not the Church, ought to be held for a Pagan, and a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. and IESVS CHRIST ſaith to S. <hi>Peter, I haue prayed that thy faith faile thee not:</hi> which manifeſteth vnto vs, that the Roman Church founded vpon Saint <hi>Peter</hi> cannot erre in faith.</p>
            <p>Diſcourſing of theſe things with my ſelfe, I thus ſaid to my ſelfe. I beleeue that IESVS CHRIST died for mee, and that the promiſes contained in the word of GOD appertaine to mee as well as to any other of the Church. Wherefore then ſhould I not dare to looke into thoſe things which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19938:5"/>vnto mee? If I had bookes of loue or fables, they would not take them from mee, and yet they will depriue me of that booke, which they themſelues affirme to be the word of GOD. And if (as they ſay) it be not to be read but by the learned, no man ſhould euer read it, ſince that no man can be learned in it before hee haue read it. I had thought that men had read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to become learned in Piety, and to attaine to that heauenly wiſdome, which out-ſhines all humane wiſdome as much as the Sunne a candle. I alſo aſſure my ſelfe that the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes were as learned as any now aliue, and as conuerſant in the Scriptures as any of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, and yet wee finde that CHRIST being demanded by his Diſciples why the Scribes, and Phariſes vnderſtood him not, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; that to them was not giuen to know the ſecrets of the kingdome of God. Yet the Papiſts would perſwade vs that a man may be learned in the Goſpell before he read it. Why do they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to me paſſages of Scripture, ſince they will not permit mee to ſee whether they alledge them faithfully or no. I would haue them to ſhew mee the places which they cite to proue the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Roman Church. As for that paſſage where the Church is called the pillar, and the prop of Verity, I finde that there is no mention at all made of the Roman Church, no more then of the Greeke, or Syrian. I may adde alſo, that there is no likelyhood that the Diuine truth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19938:5"/>ſhould be founded vpon men, it being more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient that men ſhould make the word of GOD their foundation. S. <hi>Paul</hi> by theſe words mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth onely that the Church is eſtabliſhed by GOD on the earth to maintaine, and defend the Truth againſt infidels, and enemies of the Truth: ſo that theſe words repreſent to the Church her duty, and not her authority. So the Syrian Church founded by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles was a pillar of verity againſt the Iewes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, but this did not free it from error. The ſame may alſo haue happened to the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>As concerning the paſſage, which ſayes, that hee who heares not the Church ought to be held as a Pagan, and a Publican; hee that reads the precedents, and ſubſequents ſhall ſoone perceiue that theſe words ſerue not to proue that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, which they call Catholike (that is to ſay Vniuerſall) ſhould be iudge in deciding controuerſies of Religion. Firſt, becauſe in that place the Roman Chuch is not named. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe that there it is not ſpoken of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies of religion, but of a quarrell betweene two brethren. Thirdly, it is euident that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, or vniuerſall Church is not there meant; for to take vp a quarrell betweene two brethren wee ſhould in vaine expect the iudgement of the Church vniuerſall: by the Church then in this place is meant the Paſtors, and Conductors of ſome Church particular, endeauouring to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the mallice of particular men: and it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19938:6"/>according to the precept of GOD in his word, that he, who will not conſent to what they ſhall decree, be put in the ſame ranke with Pagans, and Publicans.</p>
            <p>The third paſſage is that which moſt offends mee; for this ſeemes to mee to be a hard conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; I haue prayed that thy faith faile not, <hi>Peter:</hi> then the Roman Church cannot erre. By the reading of the whole paſſage it does appeare moſt manifeſt that CHRIST ſpeakes not at all to the Church, nor of the Church, but that hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectes his ſpeech onely to the perſon of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> preparing him for the temptation, into which he was ſhortly after to fall, that is, to deny his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. IESVS CHRIST promiſeth him by theſe words that his faith ſhall not faile him in this temptation, but that hee ſhould no ſooner fall, but that the hand of GOD ſhould raiſe him vp againe. Secondly, and if CHRIST ſhould there haue meant the Church of Rome, is it poſſible that neither that place, nor any other paſſage of Scripture ſhould mention it? Thirdly, which more is, if our faith be built vpon this ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is the head of the Church vniuerſall, and that hee hath made the Biſhop of Rome his ſucceſſour, not onely in the Biſhopricke of Rome, but alſo in the charge of being head of the Church, and that this charge hath ſucceeded in a direct line without variation of doctrine, and without interruption of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; If all this be true, I demand how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19938:6"/>ſhall be aſſured of it, ſince that to know it, many hiſtories, and authors ancient, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne are to read; which are written in a tongue which the people vnderſtands not. In this point alſo then I remaine vnſatisfied.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs confeſſe to you alſo that after I had learned that the Roman Church held, that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, and Tranſubſtantiation is not at all in the Maſſe vnleſſe the Prieſt haue intention to conſecrate, I feared much I might at one time or other commit Idolatry, knowing that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Prieſt hath his mind otherwiſe buſied, or does not beleeue himſelfe that which he does, or is a derider, and a profane man: from whence it neceſſarily followeth, thoſe who adore that which the prieſt liftes vp, adore bread, and call it their creator, and their GOD. I fell into this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity by reading the Goſpell, where I found the inſtitution of this Sacrament no way to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by the Papiſts. Firſt, for I found that in the Goſpell all the aſſiſtants did communicate; but in the Maſſe ordinarily the Prieſt alone eats. Secondly, likewiſe euery one receiued both the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. ſpeaking to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple commands euery one to proue himſelfe, and to drinke of this cup; but in theſe daies the cup is taken from the people. Thirdly, IESVS CHRIST did not lift vp the Hoaſt as doe the Prieſts. Fourthly, the Apoſtles did not adore the Hoaſt, as in theſe times the people doe. Fiftly, in the whole inſtitution of this Sacrament there is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19938:7"/>no menſion at all made of Sacrifice, nor is it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that IESVS CHRIST be ſacrificed for the liuing, and for the dead. Sixtly, IESVS CHRIST ſpake in a tongue which the people vnderſtood. Seuenthly, the Goſpell ſaith that IESVS CHRIST tooke bread and broke it: cleane contrary, the Roman Church affirmes that the Prieſt does not breake bread, but the accidents of bread, to wit, the colour and roundneſſe of bread, &amp;c. Eightly, the Ghoſpell witneſſeth that IESVS CHRIST tooke bread, broke it, and gaue it on the contrary, the Roman Church holds that the Prieſt giues not bread. 10. I finde alſo in Saint <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. and in Saint <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. that IESVS dranke of the fruite of the vine, that is to ſay, wine; it was then wine when hee dranke it: for although two cups are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, as appeares by Saint <hi>Luke;</hi> yet Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> and Saint <hi>Marke</hi> ſpeaking onely of the cup of the Sacrament cannot queſtionleſs vnderſtand by the fruit of the vine the wine of a cup, of which they ſpeake not. 11 I alſo finde in S. <hi>Paul, Cor.</hi> 10 <hi>ve.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; cha.</hi> 11. <hi>ve.</hi> 26. that wee eate and breake bread: but the Roman Church ſaies that wee neither eate, nor breake bread. 12. It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expounds theſe words in forme of a Paraphraſe, in this manner, the bread, ſaies hee, which wee breake is the Communion to the body of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>But the Roman Church denies all this, and ſaies that it is not bread, and that wee breake not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19938:7"/>bread, but the <hi>ſpeeies,</hi> and apparences of bread: from whence it followeth that theſe apparances of bread ſhould be the Communion to the body of CHRIST. 13. I finde alſo in the Acts of the Apoſtles that the Diſciples aſſembled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to breake the bread. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. It would ſeeme a thing ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the Papiſts if one of their religion, going to receiue the very body of CHRIST at Eaſter, ſhould ſay that hee goes to breake bread.</p>
            <p n="14">14 I ſee that the Ghoſpell according to Saint <hi>Luke Chapter.</hi> 22. and the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Corinthians. Chapter.</hi> 11. informes vs how theſe words <hi>(this is my body)</hi> are to be vnderſtood: for when they come to ſpeake of the cup, in ſteed of <hi>(this is my bloud)</hi> they thus expound, this cup is the New Teſtament in my bloud. The bread then is the body of our Sauiour in like manner as that which is in the cup is a Teſtament; which is not in ſubſtance, but in a Sacrament, As alſo IESVS CHRIST calleth it a commemoration, And as ordinarily in Scripture, ſignes and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments take the names of that which they ſignifie. 15 If the Cup bee the Teſtament in the blood of CHRIST, as ſaies Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> it is not then the very bloud of CHRIST; for it were abſurd to ſay that the bloud of CHRIST is in the blood of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>I will further confeſſe vnto you that when I was at the height of my ignorance this manner of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19938:8"/>ſpeaking (as to lift GOD, to carry GOD, and by the mouth to receiue the creator) ſeemed to mee harſh, and groſſe. Alſo, I could not heare without griefe ſome of the reformed religion to vpbraid vs with our Prieſts making GOD, and that they ſold GOD for a little mony in priuat Maſſes; and that if IESVS CHRIST be in the Hoaſt, he which ſteales away the Hoaſt, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſteale away IESVS CHRIST. They alſo in way of mockage told vs that our greateſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours held that the body of CHRIST might be carried away by Mice, which would make any mans haire to ſtand an end, that hath in a deare eſteeme the honour of IESVS CHRIST, our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour, the eternall Sonne of GOD. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, to affirme that CHRISTS body is in ſo many places, and that it is in euery crum of the bread, is not agreeable to the Ghoſpell, which giues him a body like to ours, that he might be our brother. They who alledge that his body is now glorified doe not conſider that when hee made this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his body was yet infirme, and not glorified. Further, his glorification hath not changed his humane nature, but hath onely taken away the infirmities of it.</p>
            <p>There is alſo another inconuenience in the Roman Church, which draue mee from it, which is, that whereas Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 10. <hi>Chap.</hi> to the Hebrewes ſaith that wee are ſanctified onely by the death of IESVS CHRIST, the Romiſh Prieſts ſay that the Maſſe is the ſame ſacrifice with that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19938:8"/>of the Croſſe, and that they ſacrifice IESVS CHRIST really, and truely for our redemption. Which I vtterly diſlike; for whereas at firſt the Romiſh Prieſts taught me that the death of IESVS CHRIST was the onely price of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, now they giue me for the price of my redemption the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is not the death of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid that the Maſſe is the continuation of the ſacrifice of the Croſſe; for then it ſhould be the continuation of the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo CHRIST ſhould die continually. To conclude, they which affirme that the Maſſe is the ſacrifice of IESVS CHRIST, ſay withall that it is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and commemoration of the ſacrifice of CHRIST on the croſſe: from whence this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence may be deriued, that it is not the ſacrifice of IESVS CHRIST: for as the application of a plaiſter, is not a plaiſter: or as the application of a medicine, or a rule, is neither a medicine, nor a rule: ſo the application of the ſacrifice of IESVS CHIST is not the ſacrifice of IESVS CHRIST. The ſame may alſo be ſaid of commemoration.</p>
            <p>Purgatory is another cauſe of my ſeparation from the Romiſh Church. I learned at laſt that the Popiſh Purgatory was built vpon this tenent, to wit, that IESVS CHRIST by his death, and ſuffering hath ſatisfied for the puniſhment of ſinnes before Baptiſme, but that he hath not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for the puniſhment of ſinnes committed after Baptiſme. I was very inquiſitiue after this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19938:9"/>doctrine; as iudging it to be a point moſt behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all for a Chriſtian to vnderſtand, ſince that it explaines vnto vs what CHRIST hath done for vs. But though with all diligence I read the Scriptures yet could I not finde there any menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all made of Purgatory. I then grew bolder, and thus queſtioned ſome of the Romiſh religion. Hath not IESVS CHRIST payed inough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from Purgatory? And if hee haue payed inough, why does not GOD accept, and take this payment for as much as it is worth? 2 And ſince that <hi>Christ</hi> makes interceſſion for vs in heauen, why ſhould not the ſoules be rather quit of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory by his interceſſion, then by the indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Pope? 3 And if (as the Papiſts hold) none of the faithfull which ſhall liue at the day of Iudgement ſhall goe to Purgatory, why cannot GOD as well exempt vs, without violating his iuſtice? 4 It is true, that nothing defiled ſhall enter into Paradis: but Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his 1 <hi>Epiſt. chap.</hi> 1. ſaith that the bluod of <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> doth cleanſe vs from all ſinne. 5 The Roman Church alſo holds that in Purgatory ſinnes are not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged away but puniſhed; it may therefore more fitly be ſtiled a Tormentary, then a Purgatory. The ordrus, and blots of our ſoules are not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, or paines, but ſinnes, of which <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> doth cleanſe vs. 6 It is neceſſary that the ſatisfaction of our Sauiour be applied to vs: but it is GOD that muſt preſcribe the meanes how to apply it, for to vs it is not permitted to inuent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19938:9"/>them. Moreouer, the ineanes applied to a thing ought to be contrary to the thing, there being no medicine which is applied with poyſon. In like maner the way to apply vnto our ſelues the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our debts by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> is not to make vs pay them. The meanes to apply to out ſelues his grace, and mercy, is not in tormenting vs in a fire. Truely the holy Scripture produceth vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of perſons receiued into Paradiſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into peace, and glory, incontinently after their death; as the thiefe. <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.29. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Timo.</hi> 4.8. <hi>and Eſay.</hi> 57. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Apocal.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. But wee finde no example of any man ſent to Purgatory. 8 The onely light which hath directed vs to finde out the errour of this Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory is experience, which ſhewes vs that it is a thing meerely inuented for gaine: for no man ſees particular Maſſes but for thoſe that giue money: poore men muſt content themſelues with gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall prayers, in which the rich haue alſo a part. The Mendicant Friers neuer goe to the funerall of a poore man, and yet his ſoule hath coſt as much, and is no leſſe precious in the eye of GOD then an Emperours. The letters of Indulgence, and perſonall diſpenſation, which the Pope grants, is not but for perſons of quality.</p>
            <p>Another thing alſo much moued mee; to wit, that a man cannot be aſſured of his ſaluation; which made mee thus to reaſon with my ſelfe. Shall I any longer remaine in a religion which (after I haue made a hurde of merits, and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19938:10"/>nay, haue bought the ſatisfactions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) cannot aſſure mee after all this whether I be the childe of GOD, or of the Diuell? what religion can this be which teacheth ſuch diſtruſt? On the contrary, through the whole Scripture GOD exhorts vs to truſt in him, and to come to him with a full certainty of Faith. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. and bids vs with boldneſſe to truſt in him with a liuely faith in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. Ephe.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>Conſider alſo, Sir, with mee, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Roman Church are much more honoured &amp; obſerued then the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of GOD. 1. Becauſe it is there taught, that the Roman Church authoriſeth the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that is to ſay, that the ordinances of men authoriſe the commandements of GOD. 2 To cate fleſh vpon a good Friday is a greater ſinne then to commit murther, or adultery; yet is this the Friday, on which ordinarily <hi>Chriſt</hi> did eate the Paſchall Lambe. 3 To blaſpheme the name of GOD in this world is a ſmall offence; but to ſpeake ill of the Pope (eſpecially in Italy, and Spaine) is an vnpardonable, and a burnable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. 4 The Iewes haue a religion which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be a couſner: but to ſay, that there is no other Purgatory but the bloud of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is a crime deſerues the Inquiſition. 5 Euery Biſhoppe of France may giue abſolution for faults committed againſt the law of GOD, but cannot abſolue men of ſinnes committed againſt the Pope, and his Sea. Alſo in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19938:10"/>Roman Church they teach things abſolutely contrary to the word of GOD, in his Ghoſpell. 1 GOD ſaith <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. Thou ſhalt not make the likeneſſe of things which are in the heauens, or in the earth, thou ſhalt not bow downe before them, &amp;c. But in the Roman Church they paint the Trinity, and kneele before the images of Saints. 2 GOD ſaies in his law, <hi>Six daies ſhalt thou labour:</hi> The Pope ſaies thou ſhalt not labour ſix daies, but ſhalt obſerue the feaſts of euery weeke. GOD ſaies by his Apoſtle. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. that a Biſhop ſhould be a husband of one wife onely, and that his children ſhould be ſubject to him in all reuerence: but the Roman Church willeth that a Biſhop haue neither wife, nor chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. 4 GOD commandes by his Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. that when we are inuited to the houſes of Infidels we ſhould eate of all that which is ſet be, fore vs, without making any ſcruple. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Roman Church commands thee, when thou art inuited into the houſes of Heretiques, not to eate of all that which is ſet before thee in Lent, and on Good-Friday. 5. GOD ſaies by his Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 14. that it is better to ſpeak fiue words in the Church in a tongue vnderſtood of the people, then ten thouſand in an vnknowne tongue: On the contrary the Roman Church ſerues GOD in an vnknowne tongue. Neither doth ſhe onely erre in this point, but in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo. But it may be, Sir, you thinke that the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19938:11"/>Multitude warrants a religion. I finde that <hi>Ieſus Christ. Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. would that we enter in by the ſtrait dore, ſaying that the way is large through which the multitude paſſeth, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to deſtruction. If you argue againſt me with ſignes, and miracles; I muſt anſwer you with my Sauiour, that an adulterous nation demands ſignes; and in the 13 of Saint <hi>Marke</hi> hee ſaith that falſe Doctors ſhould come, making ſignes, and miracles to ſeduce. If you ſeeke to conuince mee with the chaire of the Pope, I anſwere you that the Phariſes obiected to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and their ſucceſſion, and yet were the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Alſo <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſends vs not to Chaires, but to his word, ſaying in Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. that his ſheepe follow him, and heare his voyce. And in the 8 <hi>chapter</hi> hee ſayth. If you perſeuer in my word, you ſhall be truely my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Moreouer, at this day the Syrian, and Greeke Churches, more ancient then the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vant of the like ſucceſſion, and condemne the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>If you reply that in the word of GOD there are difficulties, and obſcure paſſages, I anſwere that I make my ſelfe in ſuch things neither iudge, nor interpetor, but this I am ſure that I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand inough in the Scripture to ſaue me. And I aſſure you that ſince I turned to the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> I haue learned more in two months then I did in all my life before. I haue learnd ſince to belieue no longer by another mans
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19938:11"/>faith. The conſideration of theſe odious errours makes mee exhorte you, as you tender your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to thinke of theſe things, and to deliuer your ſoule from this captiuity, to the end that you may glorifie GOD on the earth, if you deſire to be glorified in heauen. I beſeech GOD that you may be, Sir and reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FINIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble friend, and ſeruant. <hi>DISGRVSTIERES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
